Wulfgang Templene is on his way to
church.
[Music]
Just before he leaves the train, he
throws away a piece of paper. Seconds
later, another man retrieves it. He's an
agent of East Germany's notorious secret
police, the Stazzi.
And this is just a tiny piece of a
ridiculously large operation to surveil
Templan. To the Stazzi, he's an enemy of
the state. But he's not a western spy.
He's not planning the downfall of the
government or an assassination of a
socialist leader. His crime is setting
up a small group of people who want to
discuss human rights in the GDR. The
Stazzi will set up at least 10
collaborators to follow his every step.
They'll wait in front of his house in
the morning, follow him to the bakery,
sit next to him in a cafe, take the same
train, open his mail, read his bank
statements, and intercept his phone
calls. They'll type their observations
into a file on him at several Bibles
worth of text.
They'll infiltrate his friend groups,
harass him at home, spread false rumors,
pressure his employers to fire him,
threaten to take away his kids. They'll
even plan to have one of their
collaborators start an affair with his
wife just to wreck his marriage. They
don't want to put him in jail. That
would only make a murder out of him.
They want to break him psychologically
without leaving any trace.
Thei was arguably the most intrusive and
omnipresent surveillance agency the
world had yet seen. The ingenuity of
their methods is unparalleled. In this
video, we will look at all the
techniques at the disposal from regular
spying all the way to the utter
destruction of the victim's psyche.
>> Confirmed.
>> On October 7, 1949, a new country was
born, the German Democratic Republic or
East Germany. Under Soviet supervision,
the country's socialist government wants
to create a paradise for the working
class. Obstacles are plenty though.
Citizens protest against the one party
dictatorship. Thousands flee the country
to the west. Meanwhile, the Soviet Union
views East Germany as a fragile
experiment, not a trusted ally. Soviet
dictator Joseph Stalin is skeptical that
a population with such a strong fascist
past can be trusted with their own
state. East German leaders are desperate
to prove that they are loyal and
competent. And he is one of them. Eric
Milker from a rough neighborhood in
Berlin. Milker joined the Communist
Party as a teenager during the Weimar
Republic. As a young man, he cut his
teeth fighting fascists in the street.
To prove his loyalty to the party, he
even gunned down two policemen in broad
daylight as revenge for them killing a
communist. With the Nazis on the rise
and the murder warrant hanging over him,
Milka fled to the Soviet Union. He would
spend World War II in exile, eventually
working for the Soviet secret police. In
Moscow, Milka got a front row seat of
Stalin at his most paranoid, an approach
to politics Milka would later bring back
to East Germany.
It takes Milka just a few years to
become the Stazzi's chairman. He has big
plans to build a ruthless police force
so indispensable to the new regime that
nobody could imagine East Germany
without it or without him. The Stazzi is
considered the shield and sword of the
ruling party, responsible for
eliminating so-called hostile elements.
And from the perspective, there's no
lack of threats swarming all around, but
also within the country. At first, thei
openly practices violence against
perceived enemies and traders. They
don't shy away from explicit terror and
executing citizens after sham trials.
But blatant oppression turns out not to
be great branding for socialism. East
Germany wants international credibility
as an ideal state. So the Stazzi moves
towards secrecy and surveillance
instead. And this gives birth to the
arguably most intrusive and omnipresent
surveillance state the world had yet
seen.
It has been proven that people like
Templene are incorreable enemies of
socialism. Anyone who associates with
such people must be aware of the
consequences.
6:00 a.m. The observation at the home of
Central One started for Templene. This
is a regular day. He leaves the house at
7:30 a.m. He makes a short stop at the
bakery. He takes the train to a
residential building. He stays there
about an hour, then takes the train back
home. But someone is following his every
step and everything will be protocol. In
his very own file, they will give him a
code name, Central One. 4:45 p.m.
Central One left his home with his bike
and a toddler, still with his brown
shoulder back. He drove to a church
institution. There, he talks to the
pastor, and that's it. Not much more
happens after that. The agent's 17-hour
long shift ends at 11:35 p.m. At this
point, Templane has been under
surveillance for 16 years. But the
special scrutiny given to him wasn't an
outlier. Throughout the 1980s, thei had
tens of thousands of ongoing operations
on other individuals deemed suspicious.
Without context, numbers like that don't
tell us much. But data analytics are
powerful. And with Brilliant, you can
learn about it, too. Brilliant is an
interactive learning app with fun,
accessible courses in math, programming,
science, AI, data, and more. It helps
you build understanding from the ground
up. Take their data visualization course
for example. It starts from the basics,
building a solid foundation in reading
graphs, then moves into spotting trends,
comparing data, and observing
relationships. You can derive clear
insights from raw numbers, and make
better decisions grounded in logic, not
guesswork. To learn for free on
Brilliant, go to brilliant.org.
org/fern. Scan the QR code on screen or
click on the link in the description.
Brilliant also given our viewers 20% off
an annual premium subscription which
gives you unlimited access to everything
the platform has to offer. In the GDR
surveillance ran through every layer of
society. Ma even secretly surveiled the
country's most powerful men chairman
Hanukkah. Ma kept the most incriminating
information in a red pleather suitcase
just in case he'd need it one day. The
Stazzi had access to everything. Medical
records, bank statements, school
reports. But what they really wanted to
know was what people were thinking
behind closed doors. Naturally, this was
no easy feat. So, they had to get
creative.
This unassuming building in East Berlin
looks like a regular post office. The
workers inside wear postal uniforms.
They tell their neighbors they just sort
mail, but in reality, this is the
headquarters of Department M, one of the
largest operations. Inside, hundreds of
employees spent their days steaming open
tens of thousands of letters and
recording their contents. They scan and
open packages, looking for forbidden
items from the capitalist West. If they
find money or anything valuable, they'll
often keep it for themselves. Here in
this other Berlin building is the
headquarters of department 26,
responsible for acoustic surveillance.
Over 1,000 employees secretly connect to
bases like public telephones, apartments
of informants, and telephone
switchboards, automatically recording
thousands of phone and closed room
conversations at once. But they don't
actually have the staff to analyze all
those conversations. They just keep them
in case they need them later. Higher up
the Stazzi food chain, elite engineers
develop more integrate technology.
They're known as the OTS. They operate
here in this restricted, highly secured
area of East Berlin. Very few people
know what's going on and won't until the
Soviet Union collapses. The OTS
developed James Bondlike gadgets to
observe citizens when they least expect
it. Stuff like cameras behind button
holes or microphones and fake sugar
cubes. The tinier the better. If the
Stazzi finds someone suspicious, they'll
often map out the suspect's entire
apartments so technicians can plan
exactly where to hide bugs. Then, posing
as electricians or maintenance workers,
they'll gain access and install
microphones in walls, lamps, and ceiling
moldings. No corner of East Germany is
too sacred for spying. There's bugs in
doctor's offices, church confessionals,
even private bathrooms. For a while,
many would save their sensitive
conversations for pingpong games in the
park. But then theazzi picked up on that
and started bugging the trees. Ifazi
agents visit your home, they might also
take your underwear or fabric from a
chair you were sitting on. This would
then go into their archive of smells as
a scent sample. Thei keeps an entire
library of body odors. Scents, like
fingerprints, are unique. They train
dogs on the samples to track down
escapees or to prove that suspects have
been at crime scenes.
Sometimes the Stazzi agent has to track
a target without yet knowing who it is.
Or they have to tail someone in a crowd
without drawing attention. For that they
have an ingenious trick up their sleeve.
This is a quiet vibrating geer counter.
A Stazzi agent wears it under their
coat. The counter under one armpit and a
vibrator under the other. To find an
unidentified dissident or to follow a
suspect inconspicuously, the agent just
needs to follow the telltale ticking.
That's because dissident are often
tagged with radioactive material. Theazi
sprays suspicious cars or rooms and
sometimes even individuals directly with
a high dose of scandium. Once
contaminated, they can be followed using
the hidden device. The Stazzi is aware
that radioactive tagging poses health
risks, so they develop special air guns
that can spray the substance from a safe
enough distance for themselves. The
secret police is also interested in
seeing how West German money circulates.
So, they spray Deutsche Mark notes. The
idea is to retrieve the banknotes and
determine who is doing illegal business
with enemies. By their own calculations,
two notes in one man's pocket pose such
a high risk to male fertility that it
comes, in their own words, close to
castration. Later, several East German
dissident will die of rare cancers. It's
suspected to be connected to the high
rates of radiation exposure, though it's
not possible to know for sure. But the
Stazzi went even further.
Templ is visiting an old friend, Vienna
Fisher. It's not just a casual hangout,
though. Fisher's hosting the second
gathering of the peace and human rights
initiative. And Templan, who's been
interrogated and tailed by the Stazzi
before, knows the stakes are high. But
at least it's just a small group of
trustworthy people he's known for years,
like Lot Pufflitz, a good friend from
university. In the evening hours of May
17, 1987, another gathering took place
in Fischer's apartment as part of the
lecture series on Eastern Europe
initiated by Templene. The initiative
for peace and human rights is a rare
thing in East Germany, an open
opposition group formed of diverse
ideologies. It encompasses committed
Marxists who feel betrayed by their
country's undemocratic expression of
so-called socialism, but also
Christians, liberals, and other
ideologies that run counter to the
state. It makes party officials very
nervous. What Templan doesn't know,
Pavlitzak isn't here today because he's
interested in Hungarian history. He's
here solely to spy on Templene. In fact,
he's been reporting on him for more than
10 years. But Pavlitzak is not a
full-time secret agent. He has a normal
life and a normal job. He is what's
called an unofficial collaborator.
Basically, a citizen spy.
No country in the 20th century devoted
more resources to domestic surveillance
than East Germany. By 1989, East Germany
had a population of about 16 million
citizens. That year, about 90,000
officers were on the payroll, about one
secret policeman for about 177 people, a
far higher ratio than the Soviet Union
secret police KGB or the Nazis Gestapo.
Beyond the absurdly bloated police
apparatus, the network of unofficial
collaborators was even more enormous.
The country was absolutely crawling with
amateur spies, neighbors, co-workers,
even kids, discreetly betraying their
own communities. Depending on the
source, up to 200,000 unofficial
collaborators supported the 90,000
official employees and spying on their
citizens. at least one spy for every 60
citizens, possibly more. Many unofficial
collaborators were enthusiastic
volunteers who supported theazzi for
ideological reasons. Pavlitak says he
joined at 17 for a sense of adventure
and the hopes to maybe become an agent
abroad. Some snitched for cash payments
or career advancement. Others were
manipulated, blackmailed, or coerced
into becoming informants. There are many
cases of family members spying on each
other. One famous case had a husband
reporting his wife's every move to
theazzi for years. She only found out
later when she read in her file
whispered conversations they had in bed
and even details about her sex life. The
network of unofficial collaborators
created widespread mistrust and fear. In
the own words, the unofficial
collaborators were the main weapon in
the fight against the enemy.
Later this evening, Pavlitzak walks home
with another group member, Ibrahim
Burma. On the way home, the unofficial
collaborator had the opportunity to talk
to Burma Ibrahim. The unofficial
collaborator described Burma as an
intelligent person with high moral
independence. Pavitza carefully
remembers the conversation, eager to
report it back to his officer. What he
doesn't know is that Burma is doing the
exact same thing. Two spies spying on
each other. Neither the wiser. Pavlitsak
will report on Burma. Burma will report
on Pavlitzak. Both will report on
Templene. As it turns out, on this very
evening, four out of 16 participants
were working for the Stazzi.
But being all around Templene is not
enough. You see, Templane was with
theazzi himself for a while when he was
young. But after a while, he confided in
his friends uneasy about the job. Ever
since he's been branded a traitor and a
while back, Stazzi Captain Gearad Ha
started targeting him with the AY's
ultimate weapon, an operational
procedure.
It's been a few weeks since the
Initiative for Peace and Human Rights
has formed.
A man shows up out of nowhere at
Templan's store demanding to know where
he should deliver the car. He's holding
a contract with Templan's name and
signature on it for a car Templene never
ordered. A very expensive car. Templane
wouldn't be able to afford it even if he
wanted to. He used to have a great job
at the Academy of Sciences until he was
suddenly fired. The East German
Constitution grants every citizen the
right to employment. Officially, there
is no unemployment in the country,
meaning there's no need for unemployment
benefits either. Templene and his wife
try to piece together a living with
whatever odd jobs they can rustle up.
Later, Templan's file confirms that
theazzi was systematically sabotaging
his career. At first, Templan thinks
this business with the car could be a
misunderstanding. But later that
evening, his door rings two more times.
More delivery men with fake contracts.
The next day, more calls, more knocks.
In the following weeks, he'll receive
mountains of mail. Dozens of strangers
arrive with more unwanted deliveries,
more cars, electronics, valuable
antiques. Then it gets weirder. A cement
mixer, kilos and kilos of parakeet food,
tens of thousands of condoms, hundreds
of life chickens. Vulfgang has to send
them all away. Some threaten to roughen
him up. Many have traveled for hours to
reach him, and all are expecting to get
paid. It's stressful and it gets in the
way of his activism, which is of course
exactly the point and it's only the
beginning. Time for the next stage of
Templan's operational procedure.
H is typing up an action plan. Main
goals, isolating and discrediting
Templene with respect to other
initiators of political underground
activity, personal destabilization and
criminalization. It's a method developed
by Ma himself, codified as policy in
directive 1/76.
According to his manual, the goal of an
operative procedure should be to
systematically destroy the subject's
reputation, organize their professional
downfall and undermine their
self-confidence. And third, create
distrust and mutual suspicions within a
group. And Mira specifically motivates
his agents to be creative, to feel free
to ruin lives however they see fit. The
ultimate aim was to break the spirit of
rebellious individuals and groups so
that they could no longer effectively
rebel.
But Templan knows the is hot on his
heels. So against all obstacles, he
steps up his activism even more. By
December 1987, he's participating in
actions nearly every day. The Stazzi
can't keep up. The opposition is
strengthening. Civil rights activists
are acting more and more openly, and
Templane is in the middle of it all. So,
the Stazzi escalates. They get the
unofficial collaborators to up the ante
with smear campaigns to ruin Templane's
reputation as an activist. They assign
him to a spacious apartment with central
heating, one that he, hardly scraping
by, wouldn't normally be able to afford.
The goal is to make people think he's
getting paid off by Destazzi, and
they're spreading false information that
suggests he's betrayed the resistance.
Then they come for his family. They plan
to find an unofficial collaborator to
seduce his wife, Regina. Often, the
Stazzi would deploy so-called Romeo
agents, trained seducers to charm West
German women who worked in government in
order to extract intelligence. But the
Stazzi also weaponized seduction and
rumors of infidelity to so distrust and
destabilize a dissident's family. But
their plan doesn't pan out in this case.
Either theazzi never acted on their
intention or the assigned seducer wasn't
very good at his job. Instead, Regina
and Wulfgang are arrested and after no
trial or verdict, they're forced into
temporary exile. They're separated from
their children who, like the children of
many dissident, are snatched up and
placed in a home. Anything to crack him.
Theazzi called this sazetong, which
means decomposition or breakdown. Every
case was unique. Theazzi would use all
the information gathered from excessive
surveillance to harass its targets in a
hyperspecific way. All those dull hours
of surveillance enabled the Stazzi to
know exactly what would hurt a target
most. For Templan, it was his family,
his career, and his reputation as an
activist. Some victims were simply made
to feel crazy. A favorite tactic was
fortazzi agents to sneak into a target's
apartment and rearrange the furniture,
but just slightly. Clocks were changed,
fridges rearranged, just enough so that
targets would start to question reality.
Even many years after the war fell,
victims of Tazetsong demonstrate higher
levels of extreme distrust and heart
problems. Some died by suicide.
Exiled to West Germany, Wulfgang Temple
and his wife Regina were still spied on
and intimidated by Stazzi agents, but
they kept up their activism, still in
close contact with dissident back home.
Leading human rights activists were also
arrested. These arrests sparked a huge
wave of protests. The people had enough.
>> Civil rights activists planned to use
the event to demonstrate more freedom.
>> Regina and Wulgang's exile wasn't long.
By November 89, the war came down and
they hurried home to continue their
political work. This time with an
official seat at the table to help
rebuild East Germany with a democratic
vision. After Germany's reunification,
former GDR citizens were permitted to
see their Stazzi files if they could
stomach what was inside. Millions
requested their files by the mid '90s,
and many were shocked to see the names
of their trusted friends and family
members who had snitched on them. East
Germany became known as a nation of
traders. And for many, this sense of
broken trust was the deepest trauma left
from the mass surveillance. Today,
Germany is one of the most
privacyconscious countries in the world.
East Germany had strikingly high levels
of suicide and alcohol abuse. From 1949
to 1990, about 50% more East Germans
took their own lives than West Germans.
A complex issue, and to blame it solely
on the political system is an
oversimplification.
Still, the emotional damage inflicted by
the regime can't be ignored.
After the German reunification, I Mirka
was imprisoned for the murders of the
two policemen in 1931. But he was never
formally indicted for the crimes he
committed as head of the Stazzi. When he
died, crowds celebrated. His grave was
defaced within hours of his burial.
After the fall of the GDR, he said,
"Millions have died for nothing.
Everything we fought for, it has all
amounted to nothing.